<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act to hinder the reversal of several outlawries and attainders and to prevent the return of subjects of this kingdom, who have gone into the dominions of the French King in Europe.</title>
            <author>Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39291</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18367681</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18367681</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107363</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45990)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107363)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1636:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act to hinder the reversal of several outlawries and attainders and to prevent the return of subjects of this kingdom, who have gone into the dominions of the French King in Europe.</title>
                  <author>Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Crook ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVII [1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jacobites.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1691-</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107363:1"/>
            <p>AN ACT To Hinder the REVERSAL OF SEVERAL Outlawries and Attainders; And to Prevent the Return of Subjects of this Kingdom, who have gone into the Dominions of the <hi>French</hi> King in <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROPE.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>W R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>IE MEINTIENDRAI</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN:</hi> Printed by <hi>Andrew Crook,</hi> Printer to the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, on <hi>Cork-Hill,</hi> near <hi>Copper-Alley.</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:107363:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107363:2"/>
            <head>An ACT to hinder the Reverſal of ſeveral Outlawries and Attainders, and to Prevent the Return of Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who have gone into the Dominions of the <hi>French</hi> King in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">CHAP. XXX.</head>
            <p>FORASMUCH as by the Laws of this Kingdom, the Kings and Queéns of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are by Vndoubted Right, Kings and Queéns of this Realm, and ought to Enjoy the Title, Majeſty, Power, and Authority of Kings and Queéns of the ſame: Yet nevertheleſs, <hi>Richard</hi> late Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> formerly Lord Deputy, and Chief Governour of this Kingdom, by Vertue of a Commiſſion from the late King <hi>James, Donogh</hi> late Earl of <hi>Clancarty, William</hi> late Earl of <hi>Limerick, Ulick</hi> late Lord Viſcount <hi>Gallway, Peirce</hi> late Lord Viſcount <hi>Galmoy,</hi> Sir <hi>Valentine Browne, Garrott Dillon,</hi> Eſquire, late Prime Serjeant to the late King <hi>James,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Nagle,</hi> late Attorney-General to the ſaid King <hi>James,</hi> and diverſe other Wicked and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed Papiſts, contrary to their Allegiance and Duty, did utterly Refuſe to Submit to Your Majeſty's Government. He the ſaid late Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> after Your Majeſty's Happy Acceſſion to the Imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> continuing to act as Lord Deputy, and Chief Governour of this Kingdom, in Derrogation to Your Majeſty's Royal Authority, and in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107363:3"/>
thereunto; and with the Advice and Aſſiſtance of them the ſaid <hi>Donogh</hi> late Earl of <hi>Clancarty, William</hi> late Earl of <hi>Limerick, Ulick</hi> late Lord Viſcount <hi>Gallway, Pierce</hi> late Lord Viſcount <hi>Galmoy,</hi> Sir <hi>Valentine Browne, Garrott Dillon,</hi> Eſquire, Sir <hi>Richard Nagle,</hi> and others, as aforeſaid, Raiſing Forces to Oppoſe Your Majeſty and Your Government; and they with many other <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, who were in Arms, utterly refuſed to accept of the Grace, and Favour, extended to them, by Your Majeſty's Royal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, bearing Date the Two and twentieth day of <hi>February,</hi> in the Firſt Year of the Reign of Your Majeſty, and Your Royal Conſort, the late Queén of bleſſed Memory; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Countenanced and Encouraged the late King <hi>James,</hi> to Summons ſeveral of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of this Kingdom, to Meét and Aſſemble in this Your Majeſty's City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> as a Parliament; and they with others, made ſeveral pretended Acts and Ordinances, which they Term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Acts of Parliament, under the Authority of the late King <hi>James,</hi> in the Month of <hi>May,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred Eighty Nine; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Attainted many Thouſands of His Majeſty's good Proteſtant Subjects of this Kingdom of High-Treaſon, for Adhering to Your Majeſty, and Her late Majeſty; and ſeveral other pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Acts and Ordinances, in Derogation to Your Majeſty's Vndoubted Right; and Encouraged many of Your Majeſty's Subjects, to Riſe in Arms, and Levy War againſt Your Majeſty; brought into this Kingdom, great numbers of the <hi>French</hi> King's Subjects, Your Majeſty's open Enemies, to their Aſſiſtance; Murthered and Deſtroyed ſeveral Thouſands of Your Majeſty's
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107363:3"/>
good Proteſtants Subjects of this Kingdom, for no other reaſon but for their being of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and adhering to Your Majeſty, and Her late Majeſty, Your Royal Conſort, and Encouraged an unnatural Rebellion through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Kingdom, which by the goodneſs of Almighty God by the Great Expence of the Treaſure of <hi>England,</hi> and the Blood of <hi>England,</hi> and this Kingdom, and the Extreém Hazard of Your Majeſties Sacred Perſon, is reduced to Your Majeſty's Obedience, and this Your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſettled in perfect Peace, notwithſtanding which many of Your Majeſties <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſt Subjects, have Engaged with Your Majeſties Enemies, and ſeveral Thouſands of them are actually in the <hi>French</hi> Kings Service, againſt Your Majeſty. May it pleaſe Your Majeſty that it may be Enacted.</p>
            <p>And be it Enacted by the King's Moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, by and with the advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in this preſent Parliament Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by Authority of the ſame, that all and every the Convictions, Outlawries, and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainders in this Kingdom, of any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, for High Treaſon, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion by him or them Committed, or done not Reverſed or Pardoned, before the Twenty Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day of <hi>July,</hi> One Thouſand Six Hundred Ninety Seaven, other then the Convictions, Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawries, and Attainders of Perſons already adjudged, to be Comprehended within the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of <hi>Limerick</hi> or <hi>Gallway,</hi> or either of them, who have not yet Reverſed their Outlawries, and Attainders, and other then the Outlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107363:4"/>
and Attainders of ſuch, who within the ſpace of Two Years, to be accounted from the Firſt Day of <hi>September,</hi> One Thouſand Six Hundred Ninety Seaven, ſhall be Adjudged to be Comprehended, within the ſaid Articles, or any of them, ſhall be, and remain ſufficient and effectual in Law for ever, to all intents, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and purpoſes, any Error inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, or other defect in form, or matter in them, or any of them, to the contrary notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that no Iudgment upon any Writ of Error, or Plea, nor any Pardon from His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, His Heirs or Succeſſors, ſhall anywiſe operate to the prejudice, or to the invalidating of ſuch Conviction, Outlawry, and Attainders, Except ſuch as are herein before Excepted, any Law, Vſage, or Cuſtom to the contrary, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforeſaid, That all and every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt and Papiſts, or reputed Papiſt or Papiſts, that have beén Guilty of the ſaid Rebellion in this Kingdom againſt His Majeſty, and Her late Majeſty, the Queén, and who by any Inquiſition already taken, by the Oaths of Twelve good and lawful Men, and Return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or that ſhall be taken by the Oaths of Twelve good and lawful Men, and returned within the ſpace of Two Years, from the Firſt Day of <hi>September,</hi> One thouſand Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Ninety Seaven, hath, have, or ſhall be found to have Dyed, or beén Slain, in their ſaid Actual Rebellion, before the Third Day of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred Ninety One, ſhall by Authority of this Act, be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, and Attainted of High-Treaſon, and ſhall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107363:4"/>
incur the Penalties and Forfeitures that Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Attainted by the Ordinary Courſe of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceédings, in Caſes of High-Treaſon, by the Laws of this Realm, now in Being, ought to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and undergo.</p>
            <p>And be it further Declared and Enacted, That whereſoever any ſuth Papiſt or Papiſts, heretofore have beén found to have beén Slain, or to have Died in the ſaid Rebellion, againſt His Majeſty, and Her late Majeſty, the Queén, before the Third Day of <hi>October,</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Six hundred and Ninety one, by Inquiſition taken upon the Oaths of Twelve, or more good and lawful Men of the County, where ſuch Papiſt, or Papiſts have committed ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and Treaſon; that the ſaid Papiſt, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, or reputed Papiſt, or Papiſts, ſo found to have beén Slain, or to have Died in Rebellion againſt His Majeſty, and Her late Majeſty, the Queén, ſhall at all times hereafter be adjudged and Deémed, and is, and are hereby Declared to be Traytors Attainted, to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; and to have incurred all ſuch Penalties and Forfeitures of Eſtate Real and Perſonal, from the Time he or they ſhall by ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition be found to have committed, or been guilty of the ſaid Rebellion and Treaſon, as if he or they had beén Attainted of any ſuch Rebellion and Treaſon, by Iudgment upon Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, or Outlawry.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That nothing in this Act contained, as for, and concerning the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of ſuch Papiſt, or Papiſts, or reputed Papiſt, or Papiſts, That Died, or were Slain in Actual Rebellion, before the Third day of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred and Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107363:5"/>
one, ſhall extend, or be Conſtrued to extend to the Prejudice of any perſon or perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Proteſtant Religion, or profeſſing to be of the Proteſtant Religion, the Tenth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the Year of Our Lord God, One thouſand Six hundred and Eighty Nine who hath continued ſo from that time hitherto, or till the time of his or their Death, claming, or deriving any Titles of Honour, by immediate Diſcent from ſuch Papiſt, or Papiſts, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or who have, or had any Eſtates, Real, or Perſonal, by Diſcent, or Purchaſe, <hi>Bona fide,</hi> made, or who have any Real Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances on ſuch Papiſt, or Papiſts Eſtates, for Valuable Conſiderations, from, or by ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, or Papiſts, as aforeſaid Dead, or Slain, in Rebellion; or from his, or their Heirs, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors, Adminiſtrators, or Aſſigns, at any time ſince the Treaſon committed and done, and before the Sixth day of <hi>June,</hi> in the Year of Our Lord God, One thouſand Six hundred and Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Seaven; but that ſuch perſon or perſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Proteſtant Religion, in manner as aforeſaid, ſhall, and may have, hold, and enjoy all &amp; every his and their Title and Titles of Honour come to them, reſpectively, by the Death of ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, or Papiſts, as aforeſaid, Dead, or Killed in the ſaid Rebellion; as alſo all and every the Rights, Titles, and Intereſts by Diſcent, Purchaſe, or Real Incumbrance, from, or by ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, or Papiſts, or reputed Papiſt, or Papiſts ſo Dead, or Killed in Rebellion, or from his and their Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators, and Aſſigns, or any of them, at any time ſince the ſaid Rebellion committed and done, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sixth day of <hi>June,</hi> aforeſaid, any thing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107363:6"/>
in this Act to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further Declared and Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That it ſhall, and may be Lawful, to, and for the Lord Chancellor, Lord Keéper, or Commiſſioners of the Great Seal of this Kingdom, for the time being, at any time within Two years, to be Accounted from the Firſt Day of <hi>September,</hi> One thouſand Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Ninety ſeaven, to Iſſue one or more Commiſſion or Commiſſions, into all, or any of the Counties of this Kingdom, to be Directed to the Eſcheator or Eſcheators, of ſuch County or Counties, or to his, or their Deputy, or Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Lawfully Authorized; or to ſuch other Good and Lawful Men, as it ſhall ſeém meét to Appoint Commiſſioners; whereof one of the Iudges of the King's-Bench, or Common-Pleas, or one of the Barons of His Majeſty's Court of Exchequer, ſhall be always one; to Enquire by the Oaths of Twelve, or more Good and Lawful men of the ſaid County, or Counties, what perſon or perſons of the Popiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have Dyed, or were Slain in the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt His Majeſty, and Her late Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty the Queén, before the ſaid Third Day of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred and Ninety one; and what Eſtate or Eſtates, Real or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal, ſuch perſon or perſons of the Popiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as aforeſaid, ſo Dying, or ſo Killed, was, or were Seized, or Poſſeſſed of, in Vſe, Truſt, Poſſeſſion, Reverſion, or Remainder, in ſuch County where ſuch Enquiry ſhall be made, and ſuch Commiſſion Executed at the time of the Committal of ſuch Rebellion, or Treaſon, or at any time after the ſame. In every of which Commiſſions, there ſhall be a Clauſe Inſerted,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107363:7"/>
Requiring the ſaid Commiſſioners to give pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Notice in the Chief Town of each County, of the time and place appointed for the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Commiſſion, Twenty Days at leaſt, before the ſame ſhall be Executed.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That it ſhall, and may be Lawful, to, and for any perſon or perſons Claiming as Heir General, or as Heir, or Iſſue-Tail, or as Executor, Adminiſtrator, or Aſſignee, to whom reſpectively the Title, or Titles of Honour, or the Eſtate Real or Perſonal, of the perſon ſo found to have Dyed, or to have beén Killed in Rebellion, could have come, but for the Inquiſition aforeſaid, found, or to be found; and to, and for any other perſon or perſons, Bodies-politick, or Corporate, who ſhall be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieved by ſuch Inquiſition, to put in his or their Traverſe, or Traverſes, denying that ſuch perſon or perſons Dyed; or was, or were Slain in Rebellion; or to put in any other, his, or their Traverſe or Traverſes, to any matter or thing contained in ſuch Inquiſition, within one year next after the ſaid Firſt Day of <hi>December,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred and Ninety ſeaven, or within one year next after the Returning and Filing of Record of ſuch Inquiſition, as aforeſaid, at the Election of the perſon Agrieved; and if the Traverſe ſo to be Entred and Taken, ſhall be Tryed, and the Iury that ſhall Try the ſame, ſhall find contrary to the ſaid Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, then and in ſuch Caſe, ſuch Inquiſition ſhall become Void, and of none Effect in Law; and the ſaid Traverſer and Traverſers, ſhall enjoy ſuch his, or their Title or Titles or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and be reſtored and put into Poſſeſſion of ſuch Eſtate, Real or Perſonal, as would to him,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107363:7"/>
or them have deſcended, remained or come by courſe of Law, in the ſame Manner, as if no ſuch Inquiſition had beén found, any thing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And if Verdict ſhall be given againſt the Traverſer, upon any Plea of Traverſe, as aforeſaid, or if Iudgment ſhall paſs againſt ſuch Traverſer, for Inſufficiency of ſuch his Traverſe, or if he ſhall fail to proceéd to try the ſaid Iſſue of Traverſe, within one Year next after ſuch Traverſe ſhall be Filed, the ſaid Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and Finding, ſhall at all times here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, ſtand, be, and remain firm, and valid, and be no way Impeached, annulled, or ſet aſide, any Law, Cuſtom or Statute to the contrary, notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Saving and Excepting hereout, Women <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert de Baron,</hi> perſons within the Age of Twenty one Years, perſons in Priſons, perſons out of this Realm, elſewhere then in the Dominions of the <hi>French</hi> King in <hi>Europe;</hi> and alſo all perſons of <hi>Non ſane</hi> Memory, all, and ſingular which ſaid perſons, by the Authority aforeſaid. ſhall have their, and every of their Right and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reſerved and ſaved to them, and their Heirs, Executors, and Adminiſtrators reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely, unto the time that they be and come of their full Age of One and twenty Years, out of Priſon within this Land, <hi>Uncovert,</hi> and of Whole Mind.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Traverſe, or Traverſers may take, and purſue within One Year after their coming of full Age, of Twenty one Years, out of Priſon within this Land, <hi>Uncovert,</hi> of Whole Mind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:107363:8"/>And alſo, be it Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, That all ſuch perſons as be <hi>Covert de Baron,</hi> and every perſon within the Age of Twenty one Years, in Priſon, or out of this Land, or of <hi>Non ſane</hi> Memory, at the time of taking of the ſaid Inquiſition, and by this Act, as aforeſaid, excepted, that they, or their Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators, or Aſſigns, according to their reſpective Rights and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, may take his or their Traverſe, or Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes within One Year next after they reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively come and be of the Age of Twenty one Years, out of Priſon, <hi>Uncovert,</hi> within this Land, and of <hi>Sane</hi> Mind.</p>
            <p>And if they do not take their Traverſe, or Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes within the ſaid Year, and according to the Limitation, Method, and Direction of this Act, as aforeſaid, that then they, and every of them, and their Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators, and Aſſigns, according to their reſpective Rights, and Intereſts, are, and ſhall be concluded by the ſaid Inquiſition and Finding, any thing in this Act to the contrary notwithſtanding. And for the preſervation of the Peace and Quiet of this Kingdom,</p>
            <p>Be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any perſon or perſons, being His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Subject, or Subjects, who have gone out of this Kingdom at any time ſince the Tenth day of <hi>April,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred and Eighty nine, During the late War with <hi>France,</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> or any of the <hi>French</hi> King's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions in <hi>Europe,</hi> other then ſuch as have gone thither by His Majeſty's particular Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence or Command, ſhall from and after the Twenty third day of <hi>October</hi> One thouſand Six
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107363:8"/>
hundred and Ninety ſeaven, voluntarily come, or return from <hi>France,</hi> or any of the <hi>French</hi> King's Dominions, in <hi>Europe,</hi> into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, without His Majeſty's, His Heirs, or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, Licence, or Leave, under the Great Seal of this Kingdom, and that alſo, Subject to the Reſtrictions and Limitations herein after mentioned and expreſſed, for that purpoſe, had and obtained, and be thereof Convicted by due courſe of Law: Every perſon ſo Offending, ſhall be Taken, Deémed, and Adjudged to be Guilty of High-Treaſon, and ſhall ſuffer ſuch Penalties, as in Caſes of High-Treaſon, and ſhall, and may be Indicted, and Tryed for the ſame, in ſuch County of this Realm, as His Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors, by His, or Their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, under the Great Seal of this Kingdom ſhall appoint.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted and Declared, That no Licence, as aforeſaid, ſhall be good, and vali'd to any ſuch perſon or perſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the true Name, and Sir-name, and place of Abode, of ſuch perſon or perſons, where he, or they Reſided, or Dwelt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when he or they Dwelt, or Reſided in this Kingdom, is not mentioned and expreſſed.</p>
            <p>And that no Licence, as aforeſaid, ſhall be vali'd, or effectual to any more perſons therein contained, then the Three firſt named, in Caſe there ſhall be more then Three named in one Licence.</p>
            <p>And that before any ſuch Licence ſhall paſs the Great Seal of this Kingdom, the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, Lord Keéper, or Lords Commiſſioners of the Great Seal of this Kingdom, for the time being, are reſpectively hereby Directed, Required,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107363:9"/>
and Impowered, to take ſufficient Security by Recognizance, for any Summ, not under One hundred pounds, to be forthwith Filed of Record in the High-Court of Chancery in this Kingdom. That each party ſo to be Licenced, as aforeſaid, ſhall anually pay during his Reſidence, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boad in this Kingdom, to the Biſhop of the Dioceſs where ſuch perſon ſhall Reſide, whilſt in this Kingdom, the Summ of Forty Shillings for the Benefit, and Advantage of ſuch School, or Schools, as the ſaid Biſhop ſhall think moſt in want of Support and Maintenance, in the ſaid Biſhop's Dioceſs: Vpon Failure and Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof, it ſhall, and may be Lawful, to and for the Biſhop of the ſaid Dioceſs, to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute and Recover the ſaid Summ, in the ſaid Recognizance mentioned, and the ſame to lay out, and Diſpoſe of, with the Approbation of the Lord Chancellor, Lord Keéper, or Lords Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Great Seal of this Kingdom, for the time being, for the Benefit and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of ſuch School or Schools in the ſaid Dioceſs.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all and every of His Majeſty's Subjects, who at any time ſince the Third day of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred and Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty one, hath, or have returned out of <hi>France,</hi> or out of any of the <hi>French</hi> King's Dominions in <hi>Europe,</hi> into this Kingdom, ſhall on, or before the Firſt Day of <hi>May,</hi> One thouſand Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Ninety eight, Surrender him, or themſelves, to ſome One of the Iudges of His Majeſty's Court of King's-Bench, or Common-Pleas, or to ſome One of the Barons of His Majeſty's Court of Exchequer, and being of the Age of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107363:9"/>
Sixteén Years, take the Oath of Allegiance, mentioned in an Act made in <hi>England,</hi> in the Third Year of His preſent Majeſty, and the late Queén <hi>Mary,</hi> Intituled, <hi>An Act for the Abrogating the Oath of Supremacy in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Appointing other Oaths.</hi> And enter into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizance with Sufficient Sureties, for his or their Good Behaviour, for One Year thence to come; which ſaid ſeveral Recognizances, ſhall be returned into His Majeſty's Court of King's-Bench, within Thrée Months next after they ſhall be taken, or ſhall enter into ſuch Security, as the ſaid Iudges, or Barons reſpect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vely ſhall think fit to require, that he, ſhe, or they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Licenced in manner and form aforeſaid, by His Majeſty to continue here ſhall within Twenty days Depart this Kingdom, and not return into the ſame, without ſuch Licences aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And in Caſe, any of His Majeſty's ſaid Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſhall neglect or refuſe to ſurrender him, her, or themſelves, and to take the ſaid Oaths, and to give ſuch Security for their Good Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, or that ſhall not depart this Kingdom accordingly; every perſon ſo neglecting, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing, ſhall incur the Danger and Penalty of Premunire; and every perſon ſo returning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch Licence, as aforeſaid, ſhall incur the Danger and Penalty of High-Treaſon, and ſhall ſuffer ſuch Pains and Penalties as in Caſe of High-Treaſon, and ſhall, and may be Indicted, and Tried for the ſame, in ſuch County of this Kingdom, as His Majeſty by His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion under the Great Seal, of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhall appoint.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:107363:10"/>And be it further Declared and Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all and every the Eſtates, Rights, Titles, and Intereſts, either in Law or Equity, in, or to any Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, of any perſon or perſons being of the Proteſtant Religion, or profeſſing to be of the Proteſtant Religion, on, or before the Twenty Seaventh day of <hi>July,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred Ninety Seaven, and hath continued ſo from that time hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or till the time of his or their Death, ſhall be, and remain of ſuch force and effect in Law or Equity, reſpectively, and no other then if this Act had not beén made, any thing in this Act contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, and be it further Enacted and Declared, at the Humble and Earneſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>James</hi> Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> That nothing in this Act contained, ſhall extend, or be conſtrued to extend, to Confirm the Outlawry, or Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawries of the ſaid <hi>James</hi> Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> by the Name of <hi>James Power,</hi> of <hi>Curraghmore,</hi> in the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> Eſquire, but that the ſame ſhall be ſubject and liable to ſuch Order and Directions for Reverſal thereof, as His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhall pleaſe to Declare, touching and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame, as if this Act had never beén made, any Clauſe, matter, or thing therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And whereas, <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord Baron of <hi>Kerry,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Lord Baron of <hi>Kingſton,</hi> have both of them beén in <hi>France</hi> ſince the ſaid Third day of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred Ninety one, and have alſo ſince that time returned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Kingdom, and ſubmitted themſelves to His Majeſty's Obedience and Government.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:107363:11"/>Be it Enacted by the Authority aforſaid, at the Humble and Earneſt Requeſt of the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Kerry,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Kingſton,</hi> That nothing in this Act contained, ſhall extend, or be conſtrued to extend, to their, or any of their Prejudice, or Prejudices, but that they, and each of them, are hereby Declared to be Excepted out of this Act, any thing therein contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That nothing herein contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall extend, or be conſtrued, taken, or expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to extend, to Attaint <hi>Mathew Plunkett,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> commonly called Lord <hi>Lowth,</hi> who Died during the late Rebellion in this Kingdom, before the Third day of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Ninety one, any thing in this Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, and be it further Declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Enacted, That nothing in this Act contained, ſhall extend, or be conſtrued to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, to Confirm the Outlawry or Attainder of <hi>Edmond Keating,</hi> of <hi>Narramore,</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Kildare,</hi> Eſquire, nor to abridge, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain His Majeſty's Power of Pardoning him, the ſaid <hi>Edmond Keating,</hi> both as to Life and Eſtate any thing contained in this Act to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, And be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That nothing in this Act contained, ſhall Extend, or be Conſtrued to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, to Confirm the Outlawry or Outlawries, Attainder or Attainders, of Sir <hi>John Bellew,</hi> Knight, late Lord <hi>Bellew</hi> Baron <hi>Duleeke,</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Richard Bellew,</hi> Eſquire; <hi>Charles</hi> Lord <hi>Baltimore,</hi> and <hi>Robert Feilding,</hi> Eſquire, or either of them, for any Crime, or Crimes, Committed, or Done by them, or either of them, ſince the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107363:12"/>
Fifth Day of <hi>November,</hi> one thouſand Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Eighty eight; but that the ſame ſhall be Subject, and Liable to ſuch Orders and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, for Reverſal thereof, as His Majeſty ſhall pleaſe to Declare, touching and concerning the ſame, as if this Act had not béen made, any Clauſe, Matter, or Thing, therein contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided, that nothing in this Act contained, ſhall Extend, or be Conſtrued to Extend, to At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taint, or Convict of High-Treaſon, <hi>Nicholas</hi> late Earl of <hi>Carlingford,</hi> or his Brother <hi>John Taafe,</hi> Eſquire; or to Veſt in, or Forfeit to Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, Your Heirs, or Succeſſors, any Eſtate, Right, Title, or Intereſt in Law, or Equity, whatſoever; which they the ſaid <hi>Nicholas</hi> late, Earl of <hi>Carlingford,</hi> or the ſaid <hi>John Taafe,</hi> had, or ought to have had, any thing in this Act, contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That nothing in this Act contained, ſhall Extend, or be Conſtrued to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, to Confirm the Outlawry or Outlawries, Attainder or Attainders, of <hi>Nicholas French</hi> of <hi>Abbart,</hi> in the County of <hi>Gallway,</hi> Eſquire, for any Crime Committed, or Done by him, ſince the Fifth Day of <hi>November,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred Eighty eight, but that the ſame ſhall be Subject and Liable, to ſuch Orders and Directions, for Reverſal thereof, as His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ſhall pleaſe to Declare, touching and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, as if this Act had not been made, any Clauſe, Matter, or Thing therein contained to the contrary thereof notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, that nothing herein contained, ſhall Extend, or be Conſtrued to Extend, to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the ſeveral Outlawries, and Attainders, of <hi>Edward</hi> Lord Baron of <hi>Athenree;</hi> and Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107363:12"/>
Collonel <hi>John Kelly,</hi> or either of them, for any Crime, or Crimes Committed, or Done by them, or either of them, ſince the Fifth Day of <hi>November,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eight; but that the ſame ſhall be Subject, and Liable to ſuch Order and Directions, for Reverſal thereof, as His Majeſty ſhall pleaſe to Declare, touching and concerning the ſame, as if this Act had not beén made, any Clauſe, Matter, or Thing therein contained, to the contrary thereof notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, that nothing herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſhall Extend or be Conſtrued, Taken or Expounded, to Extend, to Attaint <hi>Richard</hi> late Earl of <hi>Tyrone; Theobald</hi> late Lord Viſcount <hi>Dillon,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas</hi> late Lord Viſcount <hi>Netter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> who Dyed during the late Rebellion in this Kingdom, before the Third Day of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand Six hundred Ninety one, or any of them, any thing in this Act contained, to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, that nothing in this Act contained, ſhall Extend, or be Conſtrued to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any ways, to Confirm the Attainders, or Outlawry, of <hi>Edward Geoghegan</hi> of <hi>Caſtletown, Kindaleene,</hi> in the County of <hi>Weſtmeath,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> or to Obſtruct, or Hinder his Majeſty's Gratious Intentions for the Reverſal of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Provided always, that nothing in this Act contained, ſhall Extend to Abridge, or Reſtrain His Majeſty's Power of Pardoning any Perſon Attainted of High-Treaſon, by Outlawrie, or otherwiſe, ſo as to ſave the Lives only of ſuch perſon or perſons.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>Patrick Sarsfield</hi> the Elder, late of <hi>Lucan,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Deceaſed, ſtands Indicted, and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed for High-Treaſon, Committed againſt His
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107363:13"/>
preſent Majeſty, and Her late Majeſty Queén <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be it Enacted, that nothing in this Act contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall Extend, or be Conſtrued to Extend in any wiſe, to Confirm the ſaid Outlawry, or Attainder, of the ſaid <hi>Patrick Sarsfield</hi> the Elder; but that the ſaid Attainder, or Outlawry, may be capable of being Reverſed in the ſame Manner, as if this Act had never beén made.</p>
            <p>Provided always, that nothing in this Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſhall Extend, or be Conſtrued to Extend in any wiſe, to Confirm the Outlawry or Attainder, or Outlawries or Attainders, of <hi>Henry Crofton</hi> of <hi>Longford,</hi> in the County of <hi>Sligoe;</hi> but that the ſaid Outlawry or Attainder, or Outlawries or Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, may be capable of being Reverſed in the ſame manner, as if this Act had never beén made.</p>
            <p>Provided always, that nothing in this Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſhall Extend, or be Conſtrued to Extend to Confirm the Outlawries or Attainders, of <hi>Barnaby</hi> late Baron of <hi>Upper-Oſſery;</hi> but that the ſame may be capable of being Reverſed in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as if this Act had never beén made.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That nothing in this Act contained, ſhall extend, to confirm the Outlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or Outlawries, Attainder or Attainders, of <hi>Thomas Nugent,</hi> of <hi>Streameſtown,</hi> in the County of <hi>Weſtmeath,</hi> Gent. <hi>alias, <hi>Thomas Nugent,</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Merchant, <hi>alias, <hi>Thomas Nugent,</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Montſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> Merchant, but that the ſaid <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Nugent,</hi> his Heirs, Executors, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators, ſhall, and may, have ſuch, and the like Remedy, Benefit, and Advantage, to all intents and purpoſes, for reverſing ſuch Outlawry, or Outlawries, Attainder, or Attainders, as if this Act had never beén made, any Clauſe, Article, or Matter, herein contained to the contrary, in any wiſe, notwithſtanding.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
